<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<TEI>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Turn of the Screw</title>
        <author>Henry James</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Kevin Andrew Spicer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          Originally made public by Project Gutenberg.
        </publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <p>From the Project Gutenberg's version of the text.</p>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="eng">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson>
            <persName xml:id='governess'>
              <name>The Governess</name>
            </persName>
            <persName xml:id='Douglas'>
              <name>Douglas</name>
            </persName>
            <persName xml:id='Mrs. Grose'>
              <name>Mrs. Grose</name>
            </persName>
            <persName xml:id='Miles'>
              <name>Miles</name>
            </persName>
            <persName xml:id='Flora'>
              <name>Flora</name>
            </persName>
          </listPerson>
        </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type='prologue'>
          <div type='paragraph' n='1'>
            The story had held us, round the fire, sufficiently breathless, but except the obvious remark that it was gruesome, as, on Christmas Eve in an old house, a strange tale should essentially be, I remember no comment uttered till somebody happened to say that it was the only case he had met in which such a visitation had fallen on a child. The case, I may mention, was that of an apparition in just such an old house as had gathered us for the occasion—an appearance, of a dreadful kind, to a little boy sleeping in the room with his mother and waking her up in the terror of it; waking her not to dissipate his dread and soothe him to sleep again, but to encounter also, herself, before she had succeeded in doing so, the same sight that had shaken him. It was this observation that drew from Douglas—not immediately, but later in the evening—a reply that had the interesting consequence to which I call attention. Someone else told a story not particularly effective, which I saw he was not following. This I took for a sign that he had himself something to produce and that we should only have to wait. We waited in fact till two nights later; but that before we scattered, he brought out what was in his mind.
          </div>
          <div type-'paragraph' n='2'>“I quite agree—in regard to Griffin’s ghost, or whatever it was—that its appearing first to the little boy, at so tender an age, adds a particular touch. But it’s not the first occurrence of its charming kind that I know to have involved a child. If the child gives the effect another turn of the screw, what do you say to <emph rend='italics'>two</emph> children—?”
        </div>
        </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
